Guide to the Judidth Papachristou Research Files on Alger Hiss TAM.615
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Judith Papachristou Research Files on Alger Hiss
1962, 2001-2006, undated
2001
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Papachristou, Judith
Nation Institute (U.S.)
Ruben, Albert
TAM.615
0.5 Linear Feet In one manuscript box
Alger Hiss (1904 – 1996) was an American lawyer, government official, author, and lecturer. Hiss was accused of being a Soviet spy in 1948 and convicted of perjury in connection with this charge in 1950. The collection contains transcripts of interviews conducted by The Nation Institute, and by Albert Ruben, reprints, unpublished writings by Judith Papachristou and others on the Hiss Case, transcriptions from Alger Hiss's notebooks (1984), and a copy of a 1962 letter to Alger Hiss from William Marbury.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Judith Papachristou in 2012. The accession number associated with this gift is 2012.043.
Arrangement
The files are arranged alphabetically.
Historical/Biographical Note
Alger Hiss (November 11, 1904 – November 15, 1996) was an American lawyer, government official, author, and lecturer. He was involved in the establishment of the United Nations both as a U.S. State Department and U.N. official. Hiss was accused of being a Soviet spy in 1948 and convicted of perjury in connection with this charge in 1950.
Related Archival Materials
Agnese Nelms Haury Papers, TAM 163 (R-7771D)
Alger Hiss Family Papers, TAM 314 (R-7771B)
John Lowenthal Papers, TAM 190 (R-7771C)
William A. Reuben Papers, TAM 289 (R-7771E)
A published guide to the microfilmed portions of these collections is available at this repository (call number REF E743.5.H55 P38 2006).
The Alger Hiss Defense Collection housed at the Harvard Law School Library, Harvard University consists of 115 boxes of materials amassed by Hiss's lawyers and additional materials related to Hiss's defense donated by Hiss researchers and supporters. The first three series of the Alger Hiss Defense Collection (Hiss Defense Files Series I, Hiss Defense Files Series II, and Hiss-Chambers Subject Files) are available at this repository on microfilm (Film R-7771A) and have an associated published guide (call number REF E743.5.H55 P37 2006). Materials excluded from the microfilm are available to researchers who use the collection on site at the Harvard Law School Library at Harvard University.
Scope and Contents
Contains transcripts of interviews conducted by The Nation Institute, and by Albert Ruben, reprints, unpublished writings by Judith Papachristou and others on the Hiss Case, transcriptions from Alger Hiss's notebooks (1984), and a copy of a 1962 letter to Alger Hiss from William Marbury.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
Separated Materials
There are no materials that were separated from the collection.
Interviews.; Navasky, Victor S.; Tiger, Edith; Hiss, Alger; Papachristou, Judith
- Hiss, Alger: Notebooks, Transcriptions, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Hiss Case: Articles (Photocopies), 2000, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Marbury, William L.: Letter to Alger Hiss (Photocopy), Apr 26, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Murphy, Robert: "The Hiss Case: Insights", undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Papachristou, Judith: Nation Institute Interview, Jun 6, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Papachristou, Judidth: "Who Was Alger Hiss -- Really?", 2006 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Rosenblum, Naomi and Walter: The Nation Institute Interview, Apr 10, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Ruben, Albert: Transcripts of Interviews with Individuals Associated with Alger Hiss and the Hiss Case, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Scope and Content Note
  The interviewees are: Penny Blum, Lawrence Buttenweiser, Jack Gelber, Tim Horan, Lynn Lane, Peggy Penn, Thomas F. Pike, Corinne Rafferty, William A. Reuben, Janet Schane, Natalia Schiffrin, Edith Tiger, Michael Train, Litsa, Tsitsera, and Robert von Mehren.
- The Nation Institute Transcripts of Interviews with Individuals Associated with Alger Hiss and the Hiss Case, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  The interviewees are: Grambs Aronson, Karen Brudney, Ronnie Chalif, Mary Evans Collins, Alan Levine, Victor Navasky, Gerard Piel, and Jane Spinak and Warren Scharf.
- United States. National Security Agency Website Documents, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)